"The Side Effects of Artificial Food Coloring
and Dyes: Cancer and ADHD"
Nearly 50 years ago,
Cedars-Sinai Chief of Pediatrics
Ben Feingold,
published heresy,
suggesting that
artificial food colors
could induce
behavioral disturbances.
Dow Chemical disagreed,
as did Coca Cola,
as well as other players
within the trillion-dollar
processed food industry,
who were able to convince
the medical establishment
that it was all just one
elaborate placebo effect.
But the truth can only be buried
so long.
In 2004,
a randomized, double-blind,
placebo-controlled
food challenge was published.
Hyperactivity in preschoolers
was significantly reduced
when artificial colorings
and the preservative
sodium benzoate
were eliminated
from their diets;
but hyperactivity
jumped back up
when the additives,
rather than a placebo,
were reintroduced
into their diets.
The researchers suggest
the benefit would accrue
for all children
if they didn't consume
artificial food colors
or benzoate preservatives.
Then another randomized,
double-blind,
placebo-controlled
food challenge was published
in probably the most prestigious
medical journal in the world.
This time, researchers found
that artificial colors
and other food additives
in processed foods
appeared to exacerbate
hyperactive behaviors;
impulsivity, inattentiveness,
and overactivity,
among young children,
with more pronounced effects
in 3-year-olds
relative to 8-or 9-year-olds.
And indeed, a more recent
randomized controlled trial
in 8- or 9-year-olds
in Hong Kong
didn't observe
a significant effect.
The authors suggested
it may be
because older kids
may be less sensitive,
or the dose used
was too small
relative to what
the kids typically consumed.
But what happens in children
already diagnosed with ADHD
if you remove
artificial food colors?
In a meta-analysis
of randomized controlled trials
for dietary interventions
for ADHD,
excluding artificial food colors
from the diet
significantly improved behavior.
In this meta-analysis,
the data over here suggest
that food colors were harmful,
whether assessed by parents,
observers,
or attention tests,
compared to studies
showing the opposite.
You can actually see
the difference in brain waves
on EEG compared to placebo.
As I highlighted years ago,
the European Union
requires warning labels
of potential adverse effects
on activity and attention
in children.
However, although
the Food and Drug Administration
in the United States has banned
a few artificial colors
like Red Dye No.1,
Red Dye No. 2,
Red Dye No. 4
due to cancer concerns,
no warning labels are required,
and many artificial colors
still predominate
processed foods.
Among grocery store products
marketed to children,
about 40 percent contain
at least one artificial color.
In 2021,
a report from the California
Environmental Protection Agency
highlighted the potential
neurobehavioral effects
of artificial food dyes
in children.
The authors concluded
that although not all studies
implicated them,
the current medical literature
provides a substantial amount
of evidence
that consumption
of synthetic food dyes
is associated with adverse
neurobehavioral outcomes
in kids,
and the FDA's
Acceptable Daily Intake levels
may not adequately
protect children.
For years I've been concerned
that Red No. 3
still hasn't been banned
from food,
given that it was banned
more than 30 years ago
from inclusion in any products
that go on our skin
due to cancer risk.
Finally, in October 2023,
the California Food Safety Act
was signed,
banning Red Dye No. 3
from foods and drinks
sold throughout the state,
while consumer groups,
including the Center for Science
in the Public Interest,
continue to petition the FDA
for a national ban
to prohibit use
of this carcinogen.
And on January 15 2025,
35 years after it was
banned in cosmetics,
the FDA finally banned it
nationwide in food as of 2027
and in drugs as of 2028.